a bigger transition as to how things are
done
it's very odd yeah so it's it's very
yeah it's hard to it's hard to
[Music]
it's hard to feel really that involved
it's hard to feel you know
invested do you feel that people kind of
do you feel
like it's hard to kind of keep keep
traction
when you're teaching um i ha like i have
a lot of students and i haven't been
able to
connect with very many of them very
directly it's mostly marking and
administration and assignments
and then quick zoom chats and so yeah it
all feels very
very odd hey john
hey guys how are you oh there you are
john hey
um my ear is quite bad today
but i want to keep trying to do this um
chris can tell you andrew the weather
here
has been particularly bad it's still
pretty much winter here still
so yeah my mother lives in ottawa and
she told me that there was snow in the
morning there
yeah yeah wow that's ridiculous yeah my
ear
my ears like so i might at some point
just sort of have to stabilize
but uh let's let's do this anyways i
gotta just keep doing
what i can unless it's completely
debilitating
oh i hope you don't burn yourself out uh
john yeah
yeah okay i took uh
most of yesterday off i just did one
interview thing towards the end of the
day i had an attack
while the interview was going on and i
was trying to explain to them
what was going on and they thought i was
saying that the video feed was
close and then by the time by the time
they were they sort of check thing
like because it only lasted about 15
seconds
and then then so we just went on so they
were unfazed by it
totally but i'm going to try and now
forewarn
uh any and everybody who's involved in
these public presentations that that
might happen and they'll just need like
a moment to just sort of stabilize
um and keep going eventually spring will
get here and hopefully things will
stabilize
um okay
um well maybe i could just we could just
get started
and um i was listening to your chat with
tyler hallett
um the other day oh yeah just discord
and i thought he was a very bright
fellow and had a lot of interesting
things to say and
um it made me think i
and and something that i've been
thinking about for for a while
um that i thought might be a topic that
you guys
could speak on quite well since you know
plato and aristotle and the greeks so
well and
that is the idea of of a soul what is a
soul
and how how do we how do we have a soul
in in this machine
and i i've heard you talk and kind of
redefine the notion of soul
john and does that seem like a a topic
that might be of
interest yeah i am very interested in
discussing that i'm interested in
discussing that
in connection with uh with gnosis and
uh dialectic very much very much
so maybe i could start um
try i've been talking with chris about
this and trying to
i guess it's not right with cover maybe
it's a combination uh there's a word i
want to use
and it doesn't exist in english kerry
makes use of it in his book
augustine's invention of the inner self
which of course is deeply relevant to
what we're going to talk about
um now the thing about that is carrie
takes great pains to say
well yeah this is english he wanted to
use the latin term
inventio yeah and the re and they the
publishers wouldn't let them because
well they're publishers um and
the reason you want to use wanting to
use the word inventio
is that it hangs between
our two words invention and discovery
so this is where for example you could
get around a lot of thorny problems in
math by saying
math is neither in invented nor
discovered but it is inventio
uh um so
i'm very interested then if you'll allow
me uh to
reinvent you i want to reinvent you um
the soul if that makes any sense sure um
and i want to try and
do something sort of the opposite of
descartes
so for really important historical
reasons especially
to try and form an alliance between
the catholic church and
the neoplatonic magicians from the
renaissance
descartes pretty much completely
identified the soul
with the self and then he completely
identified the self
um with the
the the the center of subjectivity the
the
the place where the mind touches itself
in consciousness you know you're
conscious by being conscious it's
pure participation and
as always with descartes when you're
deconstructing descartes
uh you have to be really really
respectful there's really
important insights there that should not
be abandoned
but that confusion of uh soul to self
to subjective center is something i
would like to try
and uh pull apart uh well nevertheless
keeping the connections
um and so um
so also the soul is connected in some
way with this notion of the divine
double
yes um or the sacred second self i think
as you you've renamed
that yeah that's very much the case
i think there's something in here that
the term uh soul is in
is aspirational um but i would also like
like more does uh christopher moore does
with
socratic self-knowledge and reconfigures
reinventio perhaps um thus
the the self as something
not possessed but to which we have a
perpetual
aspirational relation that your true
self is
is the um the virtuous self that you're
always aspiring to
right so the soul is not something we
have it's something we do
with something we it's an activity and
it's something we aspire to become at
the same time
so what i think it's what the soul
this is an idea i'm playing with serious
play and i've been playing with
christopher he's one of my
uh best pers one of the best people to
play with as you can imagine
um this idea of
i just have this image of you guys in
the in the playground with marbles
yeah yeah great great playmates in a
playdate yeah
um although i may have lost a few of my
marbles um so
uh good one yeah i'm trying and i'm
trying to pick up on
this notion that could resonate with
neoplatonic ideas of the one
within us um which i can perhaps get to
and then buddhist ideas about the no
self and the true self
um especially in the work of nishitani
and and so
what i'm when i what i'm sort of playing
with is this idea
that there's
two ways in which we participate
in a kind of transcendence one is to be
coupled to um
well put it this way the emergence of
mind is wedded to the emergence of world
and i don't mean the emergence of
thought i mean the emer like the way
the way your mind has emerged
developmentally the emergence of mind
and the emergence of the world
as an increasingly complex of complex
and dynamic set of intelligible
affordances for affinity
and aspiration so i'm going to use the
what that does is that couples us to the
inexhaustible the moreness
not just quantitatively but
qualitatively but there's also that
about us
which i want to use a buddhist term
which is our suchness
it is if this direction is the direction
of participation the moreness the
movement into mourners
this is the suchness is the is the
direction towards individuation
and the suchness is that about you
that is resolutely um
non-categorical that which that it's
it's that which you love in a person
which you love
the their uniqueness and i want i don't
like that term because it's so bound up
with narcissism
but when you pick up on the
irreplaceable
way in which that person can is and
continues to be
right and you and you and you you get a
sense of oh my gosh
right that that's the suchness the
buddhists claim that
enlightenment is you get suchness for
everything it's so it
it's a way of um
tailoring your cognition um
to
the being mode um in everything
and then what i'm playing with is this
idea that though the individual
the individuation and this is right out
of tillic and
uh chris will tell you that this
individuation participation dialectic
between the mourners and the suchness
that activity is soul between the
moreness and the suchness
yeah so you mean between some kind of
let's say
excessive life and and and just
the simple existence the way in which
the inexhaustible overflows the world
and the way in which the uh the
inexhaustible in you
overflows any categories in which i try
to particularize you
but nevertheless i'm pointing something
individuated and instantiated in you
that is not individuated and
instantiated in anything else
so this is like trying to pick up on
indra's net and other ideas
that um you presence
the moreness in your suchness and your
suchness
um that about you which
is not just not i want to use a
distinction protocol it's not just a
passive
possibility but the pure potentiality
the potential
power potency and act of being able to
right assume uh you know a variety of
identities
a variety of agent arena relationships
and also assume this in your own
idiosyncratic historical development
yeah and i think we talked about with
that with zach that the soul is
is not it's not a singular thing no no
no it's a
multiplicity it's of potentials rather
yeah
yeah yeah and so um yeah
so yeah the soul is that within you
uh well sorry one pole of the soul
sounds like dr sorry one pole of the
soul is that which in you
has this inexhaustible capacity
to do relevance realization and refit
itself in evolving fashion to the world
and then the participatory side the
resident side
is the fact and we experience it most in
wonder and ah
that the the world right
the world discloses an inexhaustibleness
that is always
presencing through it and the soul
is when those so
what i'm trying to do and chris probably
sees this
by you making use of tilik's
individuation participation and talking
about this a fining relationship
this mutual it's not reflection that
because
the moreness comes into the suchness and
then the suchness
right adds to the moreness of the world
um right it's great when you can get
this the
the handle of this vocabulary it's very
beautiful yeah
and and so what and then of course this
is deeply influenced with whitehead but
i'll
i'll say one more thing and i'll let
chris talk quickly what i'm trying to do
and again i mean this respectfully is
i'm trying to give
i guess a non-theistic or secularized uh
equivalent to what the soul's main
function was which was to worship
the soul's main function was to worship
and descartes of course left
that transformative of finding to
transcendence
right he left that out and when he
collapsed
um the soul into the self and then the
self into
the unchanging um center of subjectivity
um so i'm trying i'm trying to
reformulate reinventio soul
in a way that exacts and reappropriates
in a respectful manner
the soul's main function which is
worship beautiful
yeah and before chris speaks i wonder if
the soul ever had a kind of fixed
meaning if all of these terms kind of
they have to be reinvented all the time
otherwise they become reified and
they have they no longer have any
meaning well the problem is
things can become rarified in this way
andrew they can be embedded in a mythos
that stagnates and dies
and that has not been replaced by any
new emergent mythos
that discloses new logos right and in
that sense
they're trapped within and this is why
chris's metaphor of the dying star
is so appropriate they're trapped
they're they're they're sort of stuck on
the
event horizon if i'll if i turn his
dying star into a black hole
right yeah and so i think i think our
notion of soul
has been lost interestingly in the
performing arts you know there's a
category of music and you know this much
better than mine
i do soul in which there was an attempt
to
uh reinvent you soul as a particular way
of you know connecting um through into
music
yeah well exactly i mean you have to you
can distinguish between music that has a
soul
yeah and music that doesn't have a soul
i mean if you have a very fine
fine ear and the music that has its soul
i think is connected
with that inexhaustibility and the music
that doesn't have a soul is just a
formulaic
repetition of of something you know
it might be very performative it might
be very salient to use your term or
and that and that uh that relationship
uh that i'm talking about of worship
that individuation participation
tonos a dynamic tension creative tension
um that's very aspirational uh
you are participating in the sacred
second self while you're individuating
the current self
and reindividuating it and
reindividuating it
tapping into its suchness until you
actually come to appreciate
and become um or asymptote towards the
sacred second self
beautiful christopher i want to hear
from you i want to hear you
sometimes i'll add to that riff riff on
on someone
possibly to be added to that well i i
guess yeah
unsurprisingly what i say is just going
to be a recapitulation of what john just
said yeah
chris chris come on
humility hang on no no no i wasn't that
wasn't
i wasn't i wasn't i wasn't courting
contradiction by saying that at all i'm
just i'm just trying to say that
uh that was pretty comprehensive i i
mean okay maybe i'll
put it i'll try and put it what you did
john i'll try and maybe put
pithily i to me that
if i had to distill it down as a working
definition
i would say that the soul when i what i
understand
soul to be is like the transitive
property of the self that relates it
to its own moreness i i always come back
to thinking of soul
as a an a as a relational aspect
which helps to dislodge the notion that
it's something fixed and entity fixed
within time and space right
if it has if it's fundamental nature is
as a relational nature
both expressive and impressive then its
function in a very sort of guardian way
its function is as a relation to be
cultivated
it's as a relation as the of sort of
it it's sort of like
it is the intermediary aspect
in the orchestra of self that
bridges between the the suchness of its
current composition
to the moreness of the yet unheard
melody right
it's it's it it's the transitivity
to me is the property of the soul that
most eludes its definition
because and and that also explains it
sort of multi-vocality and its equivocal
definitions right
because it's if it's nature is as a
dynamical form of relation
then it's no wonder that we keep trying
to voice definitions on it
that it continually bucks and eludes
so so i think that the the the as
uh yeah when i think of the soul
the the best place to start for me
is to understand the soul as the
expression
of the existential and ontological
relation that we have with the aspect of
self
that is to be disclosed with the
moreness of the world
and that's perhaps why well i was
thinking when when
when john was was mentioning the soul
music and how soul music
if music has soul i mean we're not
talking about the particular genre of
soul music but just
soulful music in general it creates a
kind of silence it stops you in your
track
but there is kind of a forward movement
at the same time you feel like you're
moving and
you're still um because it's always a
double disclosure
or it's a it's a double it's what i
should say is
like the soul is your power of faith
it's the power to
it's it's the enacted power of wedding
like
the emergence of mind to the emergence
of world like i'm saying
uh the suchness to the mourners um
and so i i
i guess what what i need to say is that
it's always it's always enacted in
in faith but that faith that i'm trying
to talk
about that that ability uh
to continually
re-realize um religio
[Music]
sorry define what you mean by faith john
what what
what your working definition of faith is
well that's that's what so
i'm i'm really picking up on the arth
right
so that what faith is is faith is
right that continuity of contact
that ongoing affordance of affinity
that makes us uh conform more and more
to what we think of and what we realize
better
realize as uh real or more real
so that like i said what happens is
there we
and we these are truths that are only
tracked we can only
trace the inexhaustible through our own
trajectory of transformation
so that's the emergence the
developmental emergence of
mind as the capacity for intelligibility
and
when that is wedded to the way in which
the world is constantly disclosing
itself to us and
and then the two poles of that is
there's there's a disclosure of
what the moreness than the world can be
and then there is
and it's like two sides at the same time
but there's also a demand put on me to
aspire
to tap into the resources of my suchness
what is often called in buddhism your
original mind your
pure mind so that i find that
potential to trace
the trajectory of transframing
in a trade in a transactive manner so i
can i can more and more
maintain continuity of contact
i think it's entirely appropriate that
the definitions of faith and soul be
understood conterminously because
totally because it's it's almost as
though faith faith is a just
is the described activity of the soul
and so it's really i think it's
impossible to think of them
in as independent dynamics i think one
one is somehow a property of the other
so that the cultivation of soul
manifests in faith and the cultivation
of faith manifests in soul i think it's
appropriate to understand them
consistent in that manner i i would say
that soul
is the term for a power and
faith is a term for the virtue
uh that you know cultivates that power
towards excellence
the enacted worksheet so faith is
related to virtue
that's not very much just like this
something i wanted to ask you about
today also was this
this word virtue because in peter
lindberg's
blog there was a big discussion about
about virtue and um and he was saying
something like
um he made some kind of comment like um
he says he loves virtue more than he
could love even
a woman or his wife or if
that kind of that's what virtue means so
um
that seems to be related to faith as
well
yeah i mean so i i i
let me try something that's close and
related
um and that may help physicist um
so i think of reverence and here i'm
found following woodruff
because he explicitly argues that
reverence isn't a feeling or an
experience it's a virtue
um he's a little bit less clear about
what the virtue is but his ex
his examples um and the allusions to the
platonic tradition make clear what the
virtue is
uh virtue is and this is the other
aspect of faith that i'm trying to get
at
uh sorry reverence is the virtue that
puts you into right relationship to awe
right so that you are both excellently
receptive
and excellently that's the disclosure
and
excellently responsive that's the demand
to the experience of awe
so that you can tap into
the fundamental depths of its
transformative offering
um and so reverence is that virtue
faith is by the more encompassing virtue
uh that you know right like i say that
um alludes back to the notion of worship
where we are trying to get into a
comprehensive right relationship
um to the unfolding of
uh of transjectivity
the mutual unfolding of the
individuation of suchness
and the participation and moreness and
there's something about faith
that means that we're not there yet we
haven't arrived
we're not we're incomplete we're um
i'm trying to and i mean thomas appoints
did this right
and trying to make this notion of faith
and chris says
there it's coterminous interdefining
with soul
um trying to make the notion of faith
back into a virtue
rather than an act of willful assertion
willful identification what you're doing
is you're trying to
i think the best way of understanding
virtue is a virtual engine you're trying
to create
sense of constraints uh within
between and without that will help
give you best disposed
reliably to right relationship
with the presencing of what's most real
yeah yeah and you're becoming i mean
faith in some ways it's it's you
becoming prolifically
conversant with the
with the organization of
your relationship with the world your
relationship with
the the relations that govern and con
center
your disposition um before
let's say reality as such i see faith as
a kind of
a kind of continuity between
the state of those relations
in situ and the possibility of
transposing or transfiguring those
revelations in order to accommodate
greater levels of intelligibility
there's something like there's a
vertical continuity that you step
into when you're when your
relation becomes disposed with faith
right
it's like you're stepping at your your
you're stepping into the heraclitus
current
as it were right you're stepping into
train with something that's going to
that's going to disclose that the
possibility of
reorganizing your relations such that
you become more optimally disposed to
accommodating
the world so so that's what
here's a way of thinking what chris said
that i think would help to make it
concrete um think about
how you're faithful to your partner your
wife
that's that's a virtue right it's and
it's not
captured and and this we can talk about
this it goes back to
why you're you're you know your self
knowledge you're captured with this give
me a good thought too
for me oh i just had a good thought when
you said i didn't mean to interrupt um
when you say being faithful to your wife
um
that's an activity right yes that's an
enormous if you look inside your mind
maybe you're not always faithful you're
not
we're not always faithful right in our
in our hearts and minds
but it's what we do so that it just gave
me that that
that thought yeah it is it is and notice
how it's interdefining
interdefined with love too and yeah i
mean and that's if we make a sacrifice
on some level we might
have an attraction to other people or or
something like that
yeah but we make a sacrifice and we
decide to to limit ourselves to that
that um that relationship which actually
you know makes our horizon larger
yes exactly and that was the point i
want to make like your faithfulness to
your partner
isn't about any sense of
closure or the fact that she can be
captured by a set of beliefs
so when you the virtue of faithfulness
is to have
of course you have sentences you utter
but it's also a virtue
also requires skills
it requires a sensibility for
perspective knowing
right and and it requires a kind of cell
thing for the participatory knowing
virtues
they do they link all the knowings
together such that what's happening
is as you said you're constantly
affording your
wife's moreness
right and how but always always in
recognition of her suchness she's not an
abstract principle to you yeah so you
are affordable it's not your property or
possession
or any of those things that's right
otherwise if you have that kind of
relationship it's a relationship without
faith isn't it it is
so there's definitely not she's not
she's so she's not categorical she has
suchness
but she's also a doorway to the moreness
of the world right she's also not just
an abstract
principal she's neither just an abstract
principle or just a simple concrete
thing
she is a person which is not either an
abstract principle
nor a concrete thing but something
beyond them something like corban would
talk about as ultimately
um imaginable
so what i'm trying to say is your
relationship of faithfulness in love to
your wife
is a um it's sort of it's
it's soulful and agage you are affording
her souling
and she is affording your souling and
that's what the faithfulness is
and i mean and so in vedanta you get
this
uh taken up into you know the central
claim atman is brockman
thou are that right so that the the the
the the the mystery
of transcendence and the mystery of
imminence
the soul of the of the of the reality
and the soul
of the person are ultimately um a find
inter-affordant inter-penetrating
co-creating
beautiful yeah i was thinking about go
ahead
christopher i was just going to say it
also means that that implicit within
that within the faithful relationship is
the capacity for
the capacity for inexhaustible
reinvention
yeah of course you just find it john
right because there's something
there's something about a faithful
relationship that is necessarily
unpredictable i think about the woman
the womb with a view
expression yeah yeah right that it
always has a
the gnosis of the relationship always
has a view to beyond the relationship
and so it's just i mean it's it's it's
reliable enough
to be to be to us to as to avoid
absurdity right because when a
relationship becomes so unpredictable
then it verges into absurdity exactly
but it is not so predictable
as to become that's another kind of
absurdity
that's right yeah it's predictable total
predictableness is a is absurd and
just as subtle chaos is yeah engineering
yeah that's right that's the virtual
engineering right you're trying to steer
between those
yeah so there's something so the
property so that the the property of
faith in a relationship is that
which keeps its poises ongoing and
replenishing
right so that when you when you turn to
the relationship that's why
that's that's why faithful relationships
are a font for existential renewal in
some respect right
because you find yourself recovered and
recollected anew
in a faithful relationship precisely
because it
intermediates the moreness of the world
as well as the moreness of
yourself and so the the the capacity for
self police for
the auto poetic evolutionary quality to
a faithful relationship is precisely
that what makes it
a font of an exhaustibility yes and
notice
notice how as you are participating in
the other
right and right like chris chris said
you're also internalizing the other you
be you individuate
your suchness through your capacity to
internalize other people
yes and this is what dialogue says i
mean this is what deal
does right this is the sacramental
property of dialogue is precisely that
by the revelation of thou
you are so revealed and in your
revelation that was more revealed and
then the cycling that takes place as a
consequence of that
opens the perspective of the diologos to
the to the
to the sort of something like the
ontological vertex
that is that is available with it
with now available by by virtue of in
virtue i should say in virtue i love
that expression because i think exactly
that's it
in virtue of that faith
there's something else that i was
thinking about is that is the the uh
erotic aspect
i was just going to do that and that's
what yeah and and i i
in these conversations often we're a
bunch of men
talking it seems to be um there are
women involved as well and i hope more
and more women get involved and then
there's this invocation of the feminine
which happens
and then that seems to to bring this
conversation
in in seoul the conversation if i if i
could say so and i know that
in hebrew there i i remember that the
soul is feminine or the holy spirit is
feminine
in other languages it's masculine but
um i don't know if it's inappropriate to
i mean i i think that way all the time
in terms of masculine feminine
polarities but people seem to get
offended when you well i
i prefer the taoist polarities of yin
and yang because they
are more comprehensive they're not
limited to biological creatures um
and uh and then they also dispose us
towards
not getting overly politicized about
something important that we need to talk
about
i i was going to bring up the uh i was
going to bring up that connection
because
the moreness into suchness and
and when it sort of affines our
individuation to participation when we
get that appropriate
toenails that right relationship i think
that's
that's really the experience of beauty
where i want to bring beauty and han's
book on saving beauty and skarry's book
on
beauty i think are really really
important works on recent works on
beauty
because because what beauty is is beauty
is
exactly like scary says you know
you come upon a beautiful tree
and there's two things you say geez i
didn't realize trees could be like that
right there's the moreness but then you
you realize that this tree is somehow
in the experience of beauty unique and
different
from all other trees so right so the
tree has a soul in a sense
yeah yeah the tree has a soul and sets
not in any animism
i think animism is a for us an
inaccessible mythos
uh that that uh symbolized that uh
correctly
uh but yeah i i think in that sense it's
a kind of
animation where animation also means uh
to set things into motion
uh right uh so i think beauty is exactly
that experience it's like
most of the time we're doing relevance
realization because the goal
is to produce relevance but sometimes
the relevance realization machinery
is in the service of realization it's in
the service of disclosing the moreness
into touchness of everything
it's in service of beautifying the world
and that's a kind of flip
uh right where the
you know the work though what i'm trying
to do is actually
put myself and this is like the worship
and the reverence i'm trying to put my
relevance realization machinery
in service it's not subjectively
oriented
i'm putting it in service transactively
to the disclosure
in beauty of you know how
all of the universe had to have existed
the way it did for this
cup to be the way it is and to be here
now
the way it is and have all the
properties that it has
that you cannot possibly grasp right
here
right now and so and so
this is and this again this is a notion
of
of beauty not of consumption consumption
is the most primitive form of conformity
i become one with something by consuming
it plato talks about when you experience
beauty the conformity it's you he says
you want to give birth
in beauty the response right the part of
the right relationship is chris said his
poesis i want to create
i want to do more to afford right
more and more beauty in the world
yeah it's like beauty is like the it's
like the it's like the physionomy of the
world's moreness
it's it's what it's how the mourness
presents to us right the countenance of
the mourners is precisely what strikes
us as beauty
so and then you have a word for this
that i think i think you'd like i'm
going to give it to you and see if you
want to play
it i think in this self it's an
interface where
what we're doing we can face the world
and we give it a way of facing
us yes and also
also picking up on the technological
sense of interface
as that which defines and conforms two
things together so they can
mutually function together i thought you
might want to play with that
yeah i will play with that well i think
it's entire it's also there's something
um
in sort of a tongue-in-cheek way it's
also appropriate to this exact
circumstance because
exactly right now is interfacing um
and and and so go ahead andrew well i
just gotta say that
yeah the interface being beauty but
there's also a an ugliness to the idea
of interface as well it's like
you need to have this technological
barrier
between us or something like that that's
just a feeling i got when i when i heard
the word
yeah exactly that and so we've got to
get out
i i mean i want to bring back the face
within interface this is why i brought
up tyler in the beginning because he
was talking about this technological
platform and then i had two feelings
about that i had one feeling about
yay great little be creative and then a
other feeling of like
getting completely consumed by by this
machine that is just devouring all our
creative um
you know acts and potentials i
think that's right um i but
i think i think the technology is what
it is
in the sense sorry that sounds
trivializing what i mean is
um it is a power that has not
been coupled to virtue
there is nothing in virtue to pick up on
chris in which
yet uh that we have decided uh
you know how we're going to actualize
the potential of this you wouldn't want
it to be
ver you wouldn't want a machine to have
virtue either that in a sense that has
to be a uniquely
um well i don't know about that i i i
mean
yeah i i i actually would argue the
other way i think
as as we try to give them intelligence
we better be giving them virtues of
rationality and wisdom
but that's another argument i think what
what tyler was trying to point out is
what's happening on the discord servers
right
is a particularly powerful way in which
people are appropriating
the interface medium in order to do
interfacing
the way i'm talking about it right now
in order to try and create
um the communitas and the distributed
cognition for the reculturation of our
world
stealing the culture uh from the way it
is now frozen
in sort of um more abundant
normativities and more abundant
structures
and reculturate i mean that's what he's
based if you that's what he's basically
arguing for
and so that's what i'm trying to get at
uh
that um there's a way in which we could
virtue we could uh we could appropriate
in virtue the potential of this medium
um so that we can reculture
in a really powerful way and recognize
and re-culture and recognize
in an interdependent fashion
and so the people that attend these i'm
sorry this will actually circle back
around
the people that attend these discord
services are there
in good faith they're in good faith and
there's a
faithfulness they don't have an ulterior
motive
they're just doing it for itself because
they want to stay wedded to what's
emerging
they have a sense of they have a sense
of
finding themselves and finding the world
in the deal logos and the emerging
community around it
and so they want they want they love the
beauty of
that and they are seduced in the proper
sense of the word
by the erotic aspect of it right they
are seduced into wanting to maintain
continuity of contact with it so there's
this when you say seduction there's this
incredible darkness
and danger at the same time that's why i
don't want to forget about that right
no no no no we're talking about whatever
it is yeah
there is there is go ahead chris i think
philly
so i think in some sense philia
i think so taking the model of these
these dialogue i think is
appropriate because i think what what
the presence of philia does
is it essentially creates a matrix for
the cultivation of eros right and for
the transmutation of eras into something
like an agapic form of oesis
so you know eros eros of course can be
creative or consumptive depending on its
particular valence but i think one of
the functions of the dialogic practice
insofar as it trains and tutors
philia is that it becomes a kind of
it becomes a way of performing the
beauty of the erotic impulse in a way
that it
changes its it transforms it and and i
think that the role of philia
as a kind of intermediary between the
powerful emergence of the erotic impulse
and the possibility of its becoming in
other forms
i think is central it's i think that's
why dialogues
is focal and i think that's why the
cultivate the interpersonal
what we might call what we have called
the the horizontal dimension of
dialogues which is to say the
interpersonal dimension
of the logos the kind of thing that guy
cultivates encircling
is so it's such a fundamental starting
point because what it seems to do is it
seems to
bound the arena of play
in such a way that the eros becomes a
peritelic
exercise that can then be molded and
shaped and creatively directed
to become the birth and beauty to become
to become anagogically reproductive
and it makes me think of the campfire
again you said you said of course
there's a circle and
[Music]
of course so so there's something really
really central then
about and and i think this will come out
you know as this as this
we work to refine this more and more i
think it's going to become really
essential to understand how this is
sequenced and to understand how it
how you know what what the proper
conditions are
in order for this to happen reliably but
i think that's why there's something
about
there's something about cordoning off
the interpersonal arena
in such a way then that it becomes a
proper symbolic body
for the transmutation of eros
because you're right andrew it can be
profoundly destructive
and and it can feed it can feed and
dilate every narcissistic impulse we can
possibly have
and so it's a very very careful game
that we have to make to play to make
sure that doesn't happen
well when you were talking i was
reminded of you know my own tradition
you know
of practices of psychotechnologies which
is tantra and
tantric buddhism and of course tantric
buddhism is not about removing those
kind of darknesses or those kind of
passions or those kind of
it's not about doing away with them it's
about it's always about
transmutation of transformation exactly
exactly
so i mean the let's remember we are
talking and
it's appropriate that we are we're
talking about soul
and faith but we're also talk and love
and beauty
we're also talking about virtue and and
that's why the virtues that
are cultivated to ameliorate
and help us perhaps grow out of
self-deceptive behavior is bound up in
this reason
rationality and andrew you know that i
have a much broader view of this
yes yes yeah so i i think reason
and rationality and ultimately
you know the interpenetration of the
intellectual virtue is like
reason and the ethical virtues like
courage right
they come together in that superlative
uh
virtue which is wisdom do you know
people have to be cultivating wisdom so
dial dial logos
this is the point that uh you know that
well i i i don't mean to make it sound
like a guy is not responsive he has been
immensely responsive to it but to bring
back you know the sapiential aspiration
to bring back
the cultivation of wisdom into right
these dialogic practices that's one of
the core things of dialectic
right is to have the deep
interpenetration
of the right the
recognition we and remembering
and realization of uh
self-deception coupled to
right the participation in the overflow
that's afforded by dialectic they
they are your point andrew actually says
one of the things i've been arguing for
philosophy is not
just circling it's not just
interpersonal intimacy
and that intimacy shifts on to
intelligibility
itself and is governed by a normativity
of overcoming self-deception
yeah yeah the the the the interpersonal
intimacy is
is a symbol on it's not for itself yeah
exactly
it's put for it's it's a symbol on that
is put for
as a bridge into the service of the kind
of
self transcendence that you're
describing that's and and then when it
it's it's it's a symbol on for the
purpose of cultivating the faith of
proleptic rationality right in calarts
sense of the term and it's symbolized by
union right some kind of union um
centric symbology it's always it's an
image it's a sexual union right
of the dynamic of that dynamic process
and the you know it's it's almost it's
wisdom and compassion or or uh
rationality and
um an energy or something like that
all of those it's a wedding right it's
combining the two together
and also the picks up on this
phenomenological experience of
quasi-divine revelation
that we have in the throes of intimate
disclosure i mean that's the thing right
that's that's
that's what marks intimate relationships
of any variety platonic or non-platonic
right is that
there's something about the relationship
that
um there's something about the
the reflective capacity of that
relationship
to provide endless novelty
in the form of your own understanding of
yourself and in the form of your
understanding of the other person right
the sensibility transcendence of it
is such that it it is it is it is
endlessly dis infinitely discoverable
right there's a property of it that is
infinitely discoverable and so then that
property
becomes host i think to
the kind of infinite discoverability
that happens
in anagogi maybe home is better than
host
right um and it's all yeah that's but i
like going beyond
itself because it picks up on the
sacramental ah
valence of the exercise but i think home
is also appropriate it's both really
well that's good that's good i like that
that's really good
so i mean you know again to pick up on
the the worship
all of this is uh to you know to get
back into sort of uh
a liturgical relationship it's amazing
how religious these discussions are
becoming right
oh yeah despite the you know even though
we're where the religion
we're speaking of the religion that is
not the religion yes
more deeply religious almost the more we
get into all these things and we find
that
all these notions like faith and the
worship and
and um you know transcendence are
are really what's all about right but we
also find virtue
and we also find wisdom we also find
rationality that's why i
i almost always affix socratic
to faith socratic faith um
because that's what's so amazing about
socrates
is the way he weds himself and right to
the other
um and that's his commented on in in the
dialogues um
because he's a tip he has a suchness
about him that allows him to
reform himself to anybody he's with
right and he he's a sort of a midwife to
them he helps them give birth
but he also has this faith in the logos
he is willing to follow the argument and
this is why it also requires the virtue
of courage
he's willing to follow the argument
wherever it goes yeah
and it seems it always goes i was
reading socrates this morning
because of you guys i have for the first
time i'm reading him directly of course
i've read him through other people and
and the the last part of the chapter was
you know he comes
up to all these pseudo conclusions about
things and then he suddenly
says well we don't know actually what
we're talking about here
you know at the very end of the chapter
i thought like
there's a humor there that i i didn't
know there is there it is
this person into like thinking he had
this grandiose understanding of
something
but really the whole point was that once
you've understood something you you
don't know anything anymore
you're at the beginning again or this
gets taken up in the neoplatonic
uh practice so so the neoplatonic
universe
is one in which i think there's the
absolute pure
oneness of the one and then things
emanate they proceed out to all the
various
multiplicitous instantiation and then
everything
right returns this is not a temporal
process this is what's happening in
ontology
and the idea in dialectic because you're
supposed to do that same thing you're
supposed to project
all of your thoughts all of their
variations you have and then notice all
the differences and then recollect and
say yes
but that's just a projection and only
and then when you recollect
recollect back right and try and step
back to
what's deeper and what's affording all
of the variations
that's when you realize oh but i don't
really know it and then you gather this
is how you practice
dialect that you gather it back in and
then you again project it out so that
you externalize it you can become aware
of it
right and and then you see all the
variations and you and then you pull it
back in
and you and you don't stop you just keep
going back and forth because
you're trying to get into conformity
with how how how reality is unfolding
in that constant procession and
return and what's really cool for me is
that's exactly the main motion
in artificial intelligence deep learning
right you take some data
and you can compress out what's
underneath them all
the one and then you run variations from
that
see what sticks gather it back in
right vary it out project it out
recollected in projected out recollected
in and that's how
this that's why how these networks
evolve their capacity
to pick up on complex patterns in the
world that's what gives them their
intelligence
right right and then i guess i guess too
then that that neoplatonic process
that in that neoplatonic process beauty
is really the kind of hypostatic
emissary
right that signals the realism of that
process
and um and allows you to track and
follow it more
yeah perhaps more more um more reliably
i think it allows you not to be stuck in
your tracks somewhere
yeah it's like it seduces you forward
all the time so that you're not you're
not uh
you know you just you don't fall asleep
by the side of the road or
i think beauty is the mark of
knowing by loving right right
yeah i think that's that's its point um
and i mean originally of course the
the the the the identification was
you know purely sexually uh but of
course
what you know what chris has been
describing repeatedly to great effect
is what we're really doing is we're
exacting that and we're we're using
because we're not just biological
creatures we're cultural creatures
and we're we have to perpetually we have
to re-sacralize
the culture cultists is you know
ultimately right the place of worship
and cultivation to to you where you you
participate in something growing with a
life of its own
right all of this we have to
re-sacralize
right as we're re-culturing we're also
simultaneously resacralizing
all of those aspects of ourselves that
are properly
designated as cultural and not just
biological
and one of the and the central thing for
this
are these related terms person self
and soul those are
all ultimately i'm not i'm not reducing
them to
anything that they're coming fashion to
being merely culturally constructed or
anything like that
but they are places well they are the
primary
polls through which we interface
with culture and also afford the culture
interfacing with the reality in which it
is always embedded and upon which it
always depends
yeah well put john
yes and andrew you're right this is all
in some sense in service of the religion
that's not a religion
yes and and trying i have taken very
seriously
the the the loving criticisms made by
paul
vander clay mary cohen um and jonathan
pajot i've taken them to heart
i've noticed something and i'm really
i'm really trying to fret
a flag it and celebrate it that when i
listen to other people's criticisms and
you know and take them to heart and what
i can often do
is i can start to internalize them into
new ways of thinking new paths of
research
jonathan criticized me in that you know
i
i was talking about as if it's all
individual mystical practices
and so this is why i got so involved uh
with this
the distributed cognition it led into
the whole project of dialectic
yeah and then paul talks and
you know paul talks repeatedly of you
know the scalability problem both
developmentally and across
various hierarchies of confidence and
power
and i take that very seriously as well
it's trying to say okay
how can we reinventio all
of these polarities all these toenails
of individuation and participation
so that we can make them accessible and
scalable
yeah it's interesting i was talking to
this very
um in in paris in france very well known
um meditation teacher uh buddhist
meditation teacher
the other day and um i was talking to
him about buddhism
and my sense that buddhism in the west
has sort of gone awry
on some level um and i said what what is
the use of buddhism
um and he said i don't know maybe it
doesn't have any use
you know maybe it's it's um but but it's
just
there's i this i just love these
practices
and this kind of thing and and he said
his own teacher at shogun triple was
trying to look for something kind of
beyond buddhism right
something that would be larger and would
not be um
that would you know he would make a
meditation available
to people rather than have it being um
some kind of uh you know special
esoteric technique
yeah or something like something that's
really available to to people
or who cares if you're a buddhist or a
christian or
or whatever on some level i mean i mean
who cares i mean
well i i've been playing because i've
been doing going back to nishitani in
the kyoto school had an excellent
conversation with jared morningstar what
a great name by the way jared
morningstar
uh because i you know because he's he
for me he's
a primary example of uh you know of an
epochal philosopher bridging between
east and west
reconceiving uh you know religion
religion and nothingness i will
recommend this book until i die
it's one of the top five books i would
put it on the shelf beside playing i
just ordered it actually because yeah
and then there's some good books to
order in conjunction with it
you should definitely order uh these two
if you get a chance uh andrew there's
the kyoto school by robert e carter
[Music]
he taught in canada by the way at trent
university there's a new one the
religious philosophy of nishi
nishitani keji uh so i've been
you know really really uh playing around
with this idea
uh and uh of something
like zen neoplatonism uh because the two
the two would constantly undermine each
other sure
zen was trying to undermine itself all
the time and then you would say
then you would say there's something
called the stink of zen and that's when
you become too religious
and and neoplatonism was always always
trying to
do the same thing um uh and
and that and and and you know if we
could somehow
integrate um them together like i say
because they're not if you'll allow me
to play with the wed
wedding metaphor they're not going to
sleep easily together in the same bed
but i expect that would be actually
really really
uh a really good creative tension that
would prov
would keep well
perhaps keep a kind of criticality uh
for longer before things
everything eventually solidify right but
maybe keep the fire of criticality
burning a little bit longer
oh yeah what i wanted to say about my
discussion with this
uh this person also was that he
mentioned that you know he said each
each period that we live in has this
denial
uh denial of love he called it yeah and
he would say that you know the in the
religious era
right when people were highly religious
you know uh you would burn somebody
at the stake or or something like that
and that was the denial of love right
somebody who wasn't a christian
he burned them at the stake or if
somebody wasn't a buddhist
they were a heretic and and all that
sort of thing he says
but but but our denial he was he was he
he's written a lot about
our cultural denial today is this
commodification of everything
where where um and this pseudo happiness
uh
search for for and he was talking about
how meditation you know is usually
taught as being this
panacea to make somebody to make you
calm and
yeah and that's that's the sort of thing
and
and that that actually the spirit of it
it should be more
and that spirit of all these sorry i'm
rambling here but all these
techniques like impermanence that people
use they've they've
turned into this sort of description of
reality that's very obvious and
and stupid and they just you just use
these phrases but
but i think i think the dialogues would
you always have to keep the the the soul
and intelligence of
something i think i think so i i mean
i mean i think han has been the best
for talking about our incapacity
for love now our denial for love in um
the way in which we have turned
everything into consumption
and commodified everything and he also
has talked about
uh a correlated thing with and this
allows us to circle
back because of the way love and beauty
are bound together
uh he he has this wonderful chapter
where he talks about
um the aesthetics of the smooth yeah
we're mentioning that right yeah that we
want we want this like we want
we have we have re-identified
but his point is we have misidentified
beauty
with with making things as smooth as
possible
visually cognitively interpersonally
and his point is that what we are doing
then is
is this grand act of narcissism because
what we're basically saying is
um i don't want anything to disturb me
or disrupt me um and that's this comes
back to your point that
meditation i when i'm teaching them my
meditation classes i'm doing them i
don't know if you knew that andrew i'm
doing no i did i did
i did know that yeah i've already
burdened otherwise i would i'd love to
come but
no no no that wasn't i wasn't trying to
no no
i repeatedly tell my students you know
that meditation is not a vacation it's
an education
it should disturb you and if you're
having unpleasant disturbing feelings
good good right the people that come in
and all they want to do and they want to
talk about how they feel wonderful
you know it is appropriate at times to
celebrate
wonder and connectedness and presence
but
you should also have periods where there
is
demand and challenge on you yeah and and
and i guess you also have to go into the
underworld
that's what this guy was telling me
today about you know the poet has to go
into the underworld and
and look at the dark aspects um
of your of your world and and and of
yourself
and and all that and that's also part of
meditation which
well but you see that the the the the
you know the gnostic and jungian
metaphors are
ultimately wed to that neoplatonic
practice that i was talking about
because what do you do well how do you
really journey into the underworld well
you try to notice how you're projecting
your shadow
here's the projection and all the way
and you
it's all i mean you really can't
introspectively get out your shadow
um and and the point is that i'm taking
shadow not just
because it's too hard to look at you
mean it's it's you're not no no
because uh you you
where you have to get to a place where i
want to
play with nietzsche's thing you can't
jump over your own shadow
right it it is immersed in the very
activity
that of you're looking at your shadow
it's it's a mesh
it's like this let me give it's deeply
like this
you are so wise with other people you
can give your friend amazingly good
advice
right but trying to do that for yourself
is almost
impossible and that that's a hallmark of
wisdom where people can successfully do
that
and what you have to do and this is why
and this is moore's point about
self knowledge requires distributed
cognition and
sperver's point rationality requires
distributed cognition
because only in you like reflecting back
on me
like my projections and if we can if we
can
if we can move that from being an
unconscious process of co-identification
to an explicit one like in therapy right
only then
can i recover from my projections what
has been
otherwise inaccessible to me that's how
i can integrate
which means individuate right with the
shadow
the shadow is the disruptive things that
i have to project out so i can see them
the way like how literacy makes your
thoughts available to you
and then i can from that gather back in
and
gather in that criticality and that's
what actually individuates me and moves
me forward
i i i mean and this is what young
thought i mean
dreams are a little bit weird because
dreams are sort of other they're sort of
alternatives to your ego mind
but it's very i mean this is one of the
things when you're reading socrates
socrates spends a lot of time putting
people into aporia because he wants to
disabuse them
of all these incorrect yet intuitively
obvious ways
of how we get self-knowledge well i just
introspect bullshit
you will not get a lot of you most of
yourself will not be found
right oh well what i do is you know just
ju
you know just the things i like or
choose no
that's bullshit too right well the
things that i sort of you know
uh assent to well no that's not enough
because i don't know what you're
committed to
what the true normativity of you is
until i see you
having to interact with things that
disturb you and disrupt you
[Music]
you i mean i think moore's book is
brilliant about this it's just bringing
out
that there is so much emporia in
socrates because he's trying to get
people to
give up our feigned
and fallacious sense of expertise
about our own self-knowledge this is
what we also lost with the notion of a
soul
if you go back into you know the
christian tradition the soul was
deeper it was that part of you it was
the god-given part of you
right it was that part of you that
transcended yourself awareness because
it was that part of you
that is you know striving for
relationship to what is ultimate
god so
i mean socrates's process of emporia is
to humiliate in the old meaning of the
term
people's pretended expertise which is a
kind of arrogance
right about their own self-knowledge
because it has to be found in dialectic
i mean this is now
the convergence of this ancient argument
that self-knowledge is only available in
dialectic in this new modern argument uh
by people like sperber and my good
friend
uh greg henriques that right that reason
is reason was designed by evolution to
work within
distributed cognition not just inside
people's heads hmm
[Music]
that's very clear yeah so if you have a
confirmation bias and i have a
confirmation bias but they aren't the
same confirmation bias
you know what we'll do we will come in
with our confirmation biases and if we
prac
we come in good faith right you and i
will disrupt each other
yeah we will disturb each other out of
it in ways we can't do
with our own cognition now i'm not
saying you can't do things like
journaling
and cultivating active open mindedness
you have to do those you have to do
those too
but there's a there's a place that you
and i can get to in dialectic that we
cannot get to on our own
yeah yeah there's a place of
self-knowledge
that we can get to in dialectic that we
cannot get to on our own
because we have to disclose who we are
before another person right you have to
externalize it and we have to give up
ownership over what we're saying and
doing and let
other people appropriate it and
transform it before our very eyes
this is the thing that you you face
right when you're when you
realize the performative aspect of your
cognition it is always going to get away
from you
i i used to carry this slogan i don't
like very much i used to carry the
slogan around and use it
sort of very um uh one-sidedly but he
said you never complete a book you only
abandon it
and the one meaning of that is you can't
bring things to closure
but now i realize there's a bigger thing
because as i start to put stuff out into
the world
i realize what that abandonment is it's
those things are going to take on a life
of their own
within distributed cognition and they're
going to get to places
that i could never have gotten to with
them
i i'm thinking again of this whole thing
of
uh moses not getting to the promised
land right he's
this is our lives we build this whole
thing uh
and uh in some sense we have to deal
with the kind of disappointment
of where where we will lead to or or we
have to give up our
our you know project um
and offer it to others in a sense
yeah i think i mean part of what we need
to do
is right yeah to to
shift and this is this is my deep
i mean you know that i love the platonic
tradition deeply
but this is my deep critique of what
goes wrong
in the platonic tradition which is um
the the conjoining of sacredness with
uh perfection and where perfection is a
coming to rest
um the later christian uh neopl
neoplatonic christians replace this with
epictasis that we are
aware of where we are in permanent
self-transcendence
that god is the field that affords uh
permanent self-transcendence
and the vision of god is not to see god
in rest
but to more and more see the way god
sees so there's no final resting point
or nirvana or enlightenment or
you know here i'm i'm home now it's more
like
um continual well is there is there a
final resting point in your relationship
with your spouse
do you now say i'm done i've completed
love we don't complete any virtues we
don't
complete virtues and thinking that they
even complete us
is incorrect right your love for your
wife your faithfulness
to her those are incompletable projects
they're what they're what
john cars john carson wrote this
brilliant book the religious case about
belief
and then he there's finite and infinite
games right virtues are infinite games
they're games that are not meant to end
like a good conversation like a good
deal logos
right and virtues are always infinite
games that's one of plato's great
insights
that's why we can never be completely
virtuous only the gods are capable of
that
infinity
so that's why i can't be completely
virtuous
well but but but i don't mean to make a
joke that's that's
that's wonderful yeah um that's fine
that's that's right
well it also makes me think that our our
beauty is in our imperfection
which is kind of it's it's it's a terror
and it's a relief at the same time
well that's what rilka said right that
every beauty is an angel that's just
slightly failing to kill us
right and you know in the uh in the
asiatic there's asiatic aesthetics
of you know of wabe that you know and
this brings a broken cup or something
yeah the broken cup because
what does the crack do it reminds us
being mode of the suchness of this
right but at the same time it's exposing
us to
how everything right it's tapping into
the inexhaustibleness because
what happens when i catch the suchness
because of the crack
the cup is beautified and the moreness
of reality
speaks through it's like leonard cohen's
line there's a crack in everything
and everything yeah yeah so the light
can shine in and also in
japanese aesthetics they say that uh
it's like
a woman or a man who's just beyond that
prime
that they they consider that to be
beauty not
not something in its prime perfection of
life but if somebody
has gone just beyond the prime um so
that it contains life and death
within it it's it's it's not this false
promise
of perfection yes excellent that's
exactly right
i think that's a beautiful thing you
just said and so notice how we can't
talk about these things
without all of these all of these nodal
terms coming up
beauty love wisdom faith soul
right um
i think there's a particular
headquarters go ahead particularly
beautiful analogy to be made
um about the role of
analogically the role of silence and
the the so you know one of the things
if i can sort of use this metaphorically
at least at first
one of the things that happens in
a disclosing dialogue is that this
the silence by which you are heard
deepens and appreciates the meaning of
what is spoken
now the silence in the margins of any
given
utterance is always infinitely greater
and more
engulfing than the speech that's
proffered into it
so there's a way in which that the
silence is infinitely
appreciative of sound but
sound also contains the presence
of that silence right as though between
the notes of music as though between the
syllables of speech
and so one of the things that happens i
think when a relationship becomes
loving and faithful in all of the ways
in which we've just defined it
the silence of the relationship becomes
more and
more pregnant so you become accustomed
to speaking
into the silence of the listening ear
knowing
that whatever is spoken into that
silence appreciates by virtue of the
fact that it was spoken into that
particular
form of attentive silence and then when
and then when
when that relationship becomes more and
more knowing
its particular its particular auditing
silence becomes something that you can
internalize more and more right which i
think is in many ways what
augustine's project was with his
confessions right he's speaking
into the silence into a vow of silence
that is infinitely knowing and
infinitely knowable
and so is hearing himself heard
in the in in in the property of that
silence
and so it's like the relationship so it
goes going back to your relation
to the to the tension between such and
more for instance
that there's a way in which the tension
between such and more can be analogized
by the relationship between
sound and silence and that the more
encompassing
of silence that the sound becomes the
more the logos of it
deepens deepens deepens and appreciates
and so
to me i think that that's a way of
understanding both
the dynamic the dynamic of the
comprehending relationship
as as a as a a as a symbol on for poetic
love and it's self-transcendence
but also then its capacity to be
interiorized
as a way of performing the dialectic
interiorly because i agree john i mean
there's a way in which we cannot
we cannot self-introspect reliably to
the degree that we can do so in a
distributed fashion
but then when the distributed dynamic
becomes interiorized it does become a
way obviously internalizing the sage as
you often say
it becomes a way of cultivating that
practice it within the
within the confines of your inner life
but i think that has everything to
do with with it's not as though you're
just
importing a dialogue and then running it
online
the thing the thing that you're
internalizing is not the speech
made by the other person it's the
particular comprehending ear of silence
that they lend to your speech
and thereby pronounce its moreness
okay i want i want to riff on that
because that was beautiful and music
i i felt i felt two thoughts came to me
and that was music and clairvoyance
there's a kind of clairvoyance that
happens between uh
two people and musicians when they're
playing together and go ahead john
well i i wanna play i wanna i wanna
invoke both senses of the term
articulation
which is to you know to speak but also
to
break things into their parts right and
what chris has just
made me realize what she often does is
the way in which the silence isn't
internalized into the articulation of
our intelligibility
and yeah yeah and that the way
emporia are those moments of
depends you have to have cultivated the
correct receptivity but eporia
is those moments of silence in which you
appreciate
the moreness that is beyond you right
and and it demands a transformation for
you
and so what i'm suggesting is uh one of
the things we do in dialectic
is we learn to seek those emporias that
articulate our intelligibility
in just the way chris articulate just
the way you articulate
i'm reminded of antisthenes when asked
because he didn't write the volumes that
plato wrote
he asked what did he learn from socrates
and he said something
and all right he said well i learned how
to converse with myself
and everybody was kind of like what what
he meant was just what chris said he
spent so much time
living with socrates memetically right
that he had internalized this
socratic process and he was capable now
after only practicing it years
of doing it himself uh so so dialectic
is not
just a um a social behavior it's also
um it's it's something you do uh you
know
you speak with god in a sense or that's
what you look that's what you learn how
to do and you learn how to speak with
absolutely fine nature and that's when
you're the most that's when you're
arguably that's
that's it's that's if if the process has
there's a fruition that's
that's it yeah the epictasis i mean the
neoplatonus
it's it's all i think uh very um
implicit in plato
but the neoplatons bring out those two
dimensions very clearly
in fact they go a little too far they
tend to emphasize if you allow me the
vertical
ontological aspect of dialectic within
the the the the discourse with one's own
soul
right and that's how plato by the way
defined dialectic
you know uh uh discourse with your soul
right they tended to emphasize this but
there was that's because they had
they lived in a school and it was so
taken for granted that
the ontological right right
intrapersonal was embedded into
an existential interpersonal yeah
yeah and a community both both are
always there
mutually informing and transforming each
other chris christie
and that's something and that's
something that socrates i mean
alongside the socialized dialogues in
plato
socrates i mean i think that's what's
represented by those moments of reverie
that socrates famously has when he
pauses
for hours at a time to listen
to his diamond right that's the that's
the end that's the interiorized
exaction of the socialized dialectic uh
in the for
in the epictasis form that you've just
described
yeah socrates makes it clear that the
examination of others the socratic
examination of others is always for
reasons we've already articulated
always always also a self-examination
and socrates i forget which dialogue it
is he says
you know after i'm done talking with you
i always remember that there's a man
waiting for me at home that i have to
talk to
and that's his own soul yeah
yeah and then it kind of feeds back too
though doesn't it because for
for like the sun that the the the
dialectic that socrates carries on with
his
diamond also is what
is also what indicates the kairos of the
socialized dialogues
and the point of his entry into those
dialogues right he's guided
he's guided all the while by his inward
dialectic
and and that's what that's i think
that's precisely what tutors him
to guide the socialized dialectic as
effectively as he does right so there's
like
there are two concentric circles running
on one another
yeah i think throughout the entire
corpus i think
uh that internal dialectic you know
transforms the mind
into into an uh so it's able to achieve
a state in process that is in deep
conformity
with the states in process of
distributed cognition
and ultimately of the environment i
think
dialectic is ultimate because it is an
act of love it's ultimately about
transforming to yourself so you
more and more have the perspicacious
capacity
to enter into conformity with the logos
and then through the logos into
conformity
with ontos with being that's how you get
onto logical
you you know you you you you get into
affinity with
the logos conformity with it and then
through
the logos you get into affinity with
antos with being
and i was think just thinking as you
were speaking that it's this is very
high conceptual stuff
but also it's very simple at the same
time you know totally
it's a conversation you're having with
your wife or your children or
or or or when you know you you go for a
walk and you look at it exactly
it's not it's not it's not all that this
complexity of
concepts it's just it's being attuned to
reality right
yes that's scalability that's the thing
that paul's keeps looking for
and there's a scalability of discourse
that is scale well that's exactly it you
know
as soon as we are persons we are in
discourse because we become
persons through discourse right and so
yes this is very
in some sense it can reach up or reach
down whichever metaphor you want
into the very foundations of your
fundamental framing of reality and how
you're being
you know framed to reality and by
reality right
all of that it can reach to that as you
said this very high conceptual stuff
but it is practicable in the most and i
don't want this to sound like an insult
in the most mundane discourse that you
can engage in
this is what i mean about it being
scalable because every disc
like nobody has to be an expert in
neoplatonic philosophy
to have found themselves in a
conversation that takes on a life of its
own
and takes all of the participants to
places they couldn't get to on their own
everybody knows that everybody has the
capacity to practice
that
all we are trying to do is articulate
this
more and more and more theoretically but
also with
with practicable consequences so
we can afford it's in i know it's
enhancement it's acceptation
because of our current situation and
because of the emerging potential of
this
of these media and these new communities
of practice
we have to somehow exact ancient
dialectic
into the current you know into these
current
new communities of practice and this new
medium of communication yeah
so it's an end souling process yes
yeah back to precisely back to seoul
again
and you know and that that's a big part
of uh
making no that's the wrong verb exactly
the wrong group
that's a big part of affording somebody
becoming a person
right that insulin process and and and
what's it what's really interesting is
yeah so it's all just right sorry a
soul's not something we have that we're
born with
a soul is something we become and soul
through
through time through i like i like in
fact making it a verb the way you have
and a verb that picks up on like
connections to embodiment and enactment
yeah um yeah i think
it is and so i mean this is again
this is a way of trying to reinventio
some of the practices of theology in the
ancient world where they were sort of
practicing sort of animating things
and we look at that and go that's weird
magic and you know and i don't doubt
that there was
there was degraded forms of it in which
it's weird magic but there are also
really powerful forms of it
because you know proquest for example
says that uh
internal theo theory is way more
important than external
uh theory and what it was is about this
process
right like you said of insolving things
um
uh of reanimating them setting them back
into their proper motion
the the you know psyche is wind blowing
it's
it it's a self-moving thing when we when
we can deeply remember
sati how everything is everything is
self-moving
how the logos is not just a set but a
continual gathering
and unfolding like that that reanimation
so that we're constantly remembering the
moreness into the suchness
that was also a big part of this whole
set of
ritual practices that we dimly
understand called fiergia
in the ancient world so you're supposed
to always be practicing fioria
you know contemplation meditation
reflection
and theodia and and then that was also
ultimately supposed to lead to theosis
you're going to become more and more
godlike by doing it
yeah i i thought of the uh the
reanimating the death star again
um that image came came back to me again
well the zombie zombie is is
is is the horror of
of uh of what reanimation looks like
when it cannot be properly housed within
a world view
it's it's horrific reanimation right um
yeah
well reanimation is the wrong word um i
guess yeah in souling i like my word and
so
but so that's a way of thinking about it
is the zombie is a
is resurrection without any insolent
uh-huh sure yeah and i just had this
other
thought that occurred to me as we were
talking about the death star and
in popular culture you want you want to
you want to um you want to destroy the
death star
right but but but you don't buy the
death star you want to integrate the
shadow you want to insult the
the world right with all of its darkness
and machine
machines and and uh
find a soul in in you know the reality
of what we're living
at this time i i mean part of it
i mean the the difficulty with darkness
is
you know it stands for many things as a
term
um because there's a way in which the
darkness is to the light as the silence
is to the sound
um so that there's that sense of
darkness holy darkness
yeah well yeah yeah
and so um
yeah i mean i
there's a sense in which a lot of what
we
might think of darkness is just the
otherness of things
and their capacity to disturb us and
disrupt us
now we can either resist that and harden
against it
or we can like wilka was was saying
we can get an adaptive uh
relationship to it so that it starts to
disclose itself as beautiful
and beautiful doesn't mean comfortable
doesn't mean smooth i like that point in
the lord of the rings where galadriel is
considering taking the one ring and she
said
i will be like i will be beautiful like
the sea or what is it
you know oh yeah horrible then all men
will fear me and you go whoa
and that's the sense of beauty that
rilke was talking about
so i'm trying to get andrew that the
beauty that i'm talking about is not the
smoothness
it is exactly that kind it has awe
within
it and the sense it's not this false
luminosity or love and light
which actually is is a very dark thing
because it's a denial of
you know the other half of life
this was part of the uh the the
transformation of the lucifer metaphor
the the light bearer
and that the idea became and this goes
so much with bullshitting is that
lucifer bears the light
that misdirects your salience and and
and
right and and and makes you not seek the
good
yeah yeah
chris you were going to say something
chris say something please
i was just it's always a pleasure to
hear you talk so
no no i i was just going to say that
that yeah i mean
the idea of of beauty as something that
necessarily that necessarily destroys
and recreates yourself that if that that
the the roughness of beauty and
and also the rough roughness of love is
such that you cannot encounter it
without being so changed and if you can
encounter it
without being so changed then it has
been
it is less than um it is less than it is
less than the fullness of its nature
uh it is it is less than the fullness of
love if you can encounter it without
also being transformed
by it so there has to be a crack in
everything uh you know uh there has to
be um
like the one other those things about
leonard cohen is
his voice became more beautiful when he
lost his voice you know and
same with a lot of singers who who have
these broken voices
somehow they're more powerful when
they've been broken or
some aren't though because they
represent sure yeah that prime
but they still have even the ones that
are that are very pure or whatever still
have a
unusual strange quality to them oh yeah
they're they're not
they're not um they're surprising in
some way
right yeah i was going to say the
neoplaton is picking up on what
chris just said uh really understand the
process
uh and this is like so of giving birth
and socratic is the midwife and they
talk a lot about
the the the strain and pain of labor
that goes into giving birth and that if
you try to give birth
and think about how concept is
ultimately based on conceive
right um if you if you try to give birth
without the pain of labor you will have
a stillborn
entity
which right that's profound yeah
but it's also hopeful because yeah yeah
it's also a hopeful thing because you
can't avoid
the pain of birth right it's nothing
something that nobody can
can avoid destructive pain indicates
pain is the real indication of the real
potential
of real death that's what pain is
it's it is your mortality taking you by
the throat
and let's remember that before medicine
right before modern medicine
in a quarter of births there was a death
of the mother
of the child or the mother and the child
yeah earth was always a
very dangerous thing in the ancient
world that's why midwives are so
important because right they help to
mitigate
um our mortality um so that we can give
birth
[Music]
that's what dialectic is which is what
inflects the process
with its share of danger which i think
is something that's not
adequately appreciated about this
process about the dialect
about philosophy in general because
we're too comfortable
is that it's dangerous and and you know
and the the association of wisdom with
danger i think is not intuitive
for a lot of people um i don't know that
it would have been intuitive to me
either
before undertaking it but every instance
of it
risks a form of dispossession that is
utterly utterly
destructive and
that is i think necessarily so just as
just as love is just as love does
and so i think that um it's it's
darkness
has to be properly manifest in order for
its sapiential promise
to be fulfilled that's why it's the dark
knight of the soul
yeah and i thought of this notion of
sacrifice
um as well uh there was that was one
thing i i wanted to talk to you
you guys about as is the notion of
sacrifice and the scapegoat and because
i've been thinking a lot about that
having read the
reading gerard and ah when
i saw satan fall as lightning yeah
um and uh
maybe that's that's that's a whole other
big topic that's probably
you can't get into right now but um well
anyway what you said
uh chris struck me as quite profound but
notice what we've done
because we've enacted it we start with
this notion of soul and notice
how we've we've done all the processions
we've projected it out
right into all of these variations
almost like the projection of sound and
music
right but we're also periodically we
keep circling back and gathering back
and we're trying to find
what is the thread running is this what
is the symptomatic thread
that runs through all these projections
and thereby i can retrace back to their
origin
originating source right because
we haven't disclosed it fully of course
we haven't but you know
we've been enacted the very process i'm
talking about we cycle at we project out
we gather back in and we're constantly
doing this and we've just done it
all over seoul now have we come up have
we come out with
the
are we now in a more right relationship
with the reality
that is referred to by seoul i think so
i think so too
yeah yeah so i think i think that just
the notion becomes more evocative it
doesn't take any final form
or or or structure or or certainly not
any kind of certainty
uh attached to it yeah no it's like it's
like
we come within range of knowing by the
light of that
which we cannot define yeah
yeah i i i think it these things are
always
epic static for us we're always right
we're always
we we get a trajective sense of them in
our constant trajectory
towards them
that's wonderful but notice what you
have to give up you have to give up the
having mode the having mode is about
completable goals
right i i can drink until i am done
yeah but becoming wise like i
i i there's no doneness there's no
there's no it's final i'm complete
in fact that's that's a sure sign that
somebody isn't one
right and having something to say has to
be given up as well in a sense
yes um i noticed sort of
a silence overtaking me and then the
compulsion to speak
the the two move right um
i mean right now i i i'm tending to
speak a lot because i'm
i'm i'm very much caught up in trying to
voice
what is what i'm trying to follow i'm
there's a vocation for me i'm being
called right and i'm trying to give
voice to this calling
um the sense of being called um and i
feel a particular urgency
of how it's impregnating me and
impressing upon me
but also the urgency of the need of the
situation we're in both the meaning
crisis and the particular
the way it's being accelerated by the
covid crisis um
but i appreciate what you're saying
andrew um
i think i i didn't mean that as a
criticism
or to suggest that you were speaking too
much too much i'm just saying
it's almost like there's a compulsion to
speak and you have to you have to stop
yourself and say
what what why am i speaking what is the
you know am i adding anything to this
conversation
speaking but i feel that you're being
animated by something beyond that so
so i i never questioned that in in what
you were saying
i i just want to reish i guess i was
trying to offer reassurance that
um i am trying to cultivate a sense
where
i am receptive to being struck by people
by insight connection criticism and
commentary that they give
such that i will take it to heart if i
have good plausible reason to believe it
was given in good faith
that's a standard that's a virtue i'm
trying to cultivate yeah
and multiple times in this conversation
you've seen me i'm struck by what
either one of you have said something
it's like oh wow yeah
yeah me too and well and also also chris
has been much
quieter in this conversation and um part
of me is like wanting you to speak
more because because you have such a way
with words on the other on the other
hand i
i think there's a dignity at other times
in just
um you know uh being present in the
conversation and that adds something to
the conversation
as much as words would add to the
conversation
i think so yeah because i i mean well i
was just going to say chris listen's
better than anybody that i know
he really does thank you come on i mean
that's not just me
as a compliment under friendship you
listen in this deeply
responsive and receptive way right and
and
and and and you you take it to heart
like i've been saying and you come point
so when you come back
um after the silence i mean that's why
it was that's why you spoke of this art
because you come back out of the silence
right um yeah yeah in in
in in like
and you speak in virtue of it and you
speak right yeah
or or or try to yeah yeah well exactly
no i i
thank you for thank you for saying it
that way i think um
because because to me identifying with
the rhythm of the dialogues
doesn't always mean being its voice
right because because the listening ear
is that
to me like the idea logos the dialogue
takes
the the various dialogists and collapses
them
into an entity so that the listening
voice
and the the sorry the speaking voice and
the listening ear
collapse into unity and so the unity
of the list the listening ear and the
speaking voice is such that partaking of
the rhythm of the conversation
can simply be that can simply be being
its form of silence
being its form of listening silence and
um
and you're right i and and i have this i
i share your
feeling andrew of wanting to make sure
that
that anytime this speech is offered
that it is offered in
that it's that it's tuned to the rhythm
of the dialogue
so that it contributes to the evolution
of the melody
and it doesn't interrupt it or if it
does interrupt it it interrupts it in
order to pivot it
meaningfully and not gratuitously so i
like that's that's so important to me
the economy
of dialogues is really really important
to me and
and and because i think it's something
that has to be finessed and it's
something you can you can
get better at and you can get more more
fluent in
so i think yeah reticence is not
reticence is not um reticence is not
fear or trepidation most of the time
it's just
it's it's just wait it's waiting for the
chiropractic opportunity
where the voice becomes an essential
part of the dialogic evolution
um and and and therein big dignifies
itself
you know so so i got this powerful image
out of this and i don't know if you were
attending it
uh you know this notion of the way the
greek chorus
bears witness uh because in dialectic
all the people that are
not speaking are basically the greek
chorus
bearing witness in a reflective fashion
and always
poised to you know disturb
what the speaker has done or or
like they're meant to call the speaker
out
in both meanings of the word they're men
and they're right here now and
uh they're here and uh they're with us
in a sense yes exactly
exactly right i'm playing on this notion
of calling out when you call somebody
out and
that means you're trying to draw them
but you're also calling them into giving
an account
right of themselves and being
responsible like i'm calling you out
right um and and so i mean that that's
how i understand the function of the
greek chorus
and what i was hearing when chris was i
just got this image
when he was talking about uh you know
all the people participating for example
in a dialectic that
the the what's happening is you know
momentarily this person is the speaker
right in the greek and then you all the
other people are the
the greek chorus bearing witness and and
people often and
it's telling that we don't understand
the dramatic function of the greek
chorus any
anymore um so chris was i correct in
picking up on that illusion ah yeah yeah
no i think so
i think so because i i think what the
chorus does
i mean there's a reason that that the
traditional function of the greek chorus
is in part
a a
um a wordless ex well they're not always
wordless sometimes they speak but when
they don't speak they are a wordless
expression of the dramatic irony
that knows the circumstances of the plot
beyond its own knowing
so right you listen for like the the
greek chorus hears everything that is
not said as opposed to everything that
is said
and so they represe again they represent
the form of proleptic
knowing that sees the meta meaning
of the narrative beyond the beyond the
meaning that the characters are living
out
right right so the representation of
that presence in a dialogue i think is
very
important because it hears and sees
everything
that is that is yet unsaid that is yet
unspoken that has not yet been shown
forth and so the presence
the presence of that person shows forth
the dialogues
to patterns that it has not yet espoused
just as the greek chorus with their eye
to dramatic irony
can see the meta meaningfulness of the
narrative that is not available to the
characters that are being born out
through it
that's amazing yes
and it gives me a slight insight into
why
why we're doing this as well because
we're not just doing this
for ourselves or for some egocentric
reason even though it might appear that
like putting our putting videos on
youtube
because there is there is this chorus
around us there is this
multiplicity of voices that we are
responsible to
or that that are that are
i don't know if i've articulated that no
i think that's exactly right
that's the weird symbol on of this
medium andrew
like i mean think about well think about
socrates
he doesn't want to write anything down
because he thought the permanence of
text
would like choke off the life
of lo of logos right uh plato of course
then
ironically especially in a dramatically
ironic sense
uh went ahead to write all these dramas
um
but what we are doing is we are doing
the
the we're you know we are in seouling
speech
here in via logos and it has that
you know if effervescent but ephemeral
quality of conversation
but it's also being made permanent by
recording we are joining together it's
also a performance of some kind
it absolutely is like it's not just
we're talking to each other uh
oh no it kind of seems that way gonna be
taken up and have a life of itself
beyond us normally when conversation
ended the only life it had was in the
memory of the participants
now like text it will have a life of its
own independent
of our authorship and that means we are
bridging between the two things that
plato saw is oppositional
we are getting the permanency of text
but we're getting the living breath
of dialogue and we're getting theater
because we need theater
i mean this is what's missing in our
culture as real
theater and i think that is what almost
was compelling us to talk like this and
and it's appropriate that that chris
christophe would use these theatrical
metaphors because
um you know all of the life is a stage
it also i think fits the dialogic
process with its
share of danger we were talking before
about the fact that you know in order to
be
changed by something it ha you have to
you have to risk
dispossession and you have to risk there
has to be something
deleterious about it and i think that
that's the public nature of it
actually fits it with that quality
because there is
or i don't know if you guys feel i still
feel that every time i do one of these
things i
feel a sense a very pregnant sense
of risk i feel a very pregnant sense of
danger and to me
to me that's essential that's essential
i think
civilized said something very very
eloquent about this too in terms of
of course that the public nature is what
actually allows for
the uh is what is what
um the the
the public nature of these dialogues
is precisely what opens them to the
possibility of dynamic
quality because you have to you you're
you're walking and the knife edge
and um and so the the
and and i think there's some kind of
there's some kind of
artful balance or equilibration that
some dialogues strike better than others
depending on the amount of awareness
that the dialogue
accommodates of the witnessing presence
of the chorus that sees it from without
and and and every dialogue is a little
different how each dialogue accommodates
that presence is a little bit different
some seem to kind of carry on almost
heedless of it
some are so hyper aware of it that they
become so
fraught with their their fore knowing
sense of risk
that they become almost inhibited by it
but there's some
something down the middle of those two
and when that
catches properly i think that the the
fear of exposure
um risked by the perspective that sees
this from without
is is part of what helps to insole it
with its possibility
because perhaps if you make yourself
vulnerable as well and if
with through our sincerity you also
become the potential object for ridicul
ridicule or the potential scapegoat um
totally totally but that's the virtue
again the virtue
virtue is what steers you between the
you know the vices
of deficiency and the vices of uh
you know uh excess right
and and and i'm thinking here that part
of what
the chorus does i mean
the chorus so the the the
hero is on center stage the way the hero
archetype is on center stage right now
on a lot of these discourse
and i keep trying to remind people that
the heroic myth always needs to be
counterbalanced with the hubris
myths and i think that chorus often
speaks the voice of
the warning of hubris to counter about
that's definitely what's happening in
the tragedies
to counterbalance right the heroism of
the hero
and and and you're supposed to you right
the the hero especially in the tragedy
ultimately is defeated
but right and this is sort of more of a
niching interpretation than an
aristotelian
but the point is that the the the person
who's partaking
in right the drama watching the drama
right actually gets steered between
right hubris and an overblown heroism
and right so they don't they're not a
coward
uh because they admire the beauty of the
hero but they remember the mortality
because the chorus speaks
of hubris and we witness it's what we
witness its effects so i think there's
something important about
um the way we have this invisible chorus
around us right now
because it really helps uh us cultivate
a virtue
in which like a kind of courage where
we're
not hyper-vigilant and they're therefore
terrorized
into timidity or we are just overblown
and just speaking um in some reckless
and heedless fashion
so so the word that came to me is is um
the chorus
keeps you humble uh humility
um but also also not not
um
well it encourages there's some part if
you're part of a chorus you're part of a
a grand story at the same time so
there's this humility and there's this
this
this uh you know this um
i don't know dramatic grandiose you're
right yes
yes excitement about life or
what it does i think it's actually it's
a higher order of relevance
it it represents a higher order of
relevance
that then is that then is is is is
gifted
to the dialogue very much very much i
was going to say that
in addition to the humiliation of the
hero
the chorus also honors the hero right
um it's right the chorus will often
um you know uh bespeak
um the the the some of the virtues of
the hero
so the the right i i just want to say
this because i don't want to i don't i
don't want to make
portray the chorus as just something
that's humiliating the hero
the chorus also honors the hero the the
chorus reminds us
the chorus will often remind us of
elements of the hero's path that have
rendered him
heroic in important ways um so i just
wanted to nuance that a bit andrew the
the chorus is doing that you know that
presentation of hubris
uh but it's also bound up with a
recognition
on honoring of the hero uh if so i'm
trying to make it
what i'm trying to say here here this is
what i want to say
the relationship between the hero and
the chorus is not adversarial it's
opponent processing
component processing it's a process
that's it's supposed to be a
self-correcting process
i wonder if it's something like the
relationship between the individual
instrumentalist and the conductor
of the orchestra something like that
yeah
i mean a really good book on all of this
um
how important this is is uh this book
uh bearing witness to epiphany persons
things and the nature of erotic life
and he doesn't mean sexual eroticism uh
this is john rusin's
uh book he's also works in canada at
least he did when he wrote this book and
this whole notion of bearing witness to
epiphany
right which is bringing together so much
of what we've said and how
it's so central a process bearing
witness in this right way
is one of the deep ways in which we
inculcate people and
in which we we turn them into persons
so maybe the the chorus is a person
um generating function
i think chris is right it's the it's an
overarching
a higher order relevance realization um
that is yeah contributing to um
the cultivation of personhood yeah yeah
very much and it reminds us what
it reminds us what what is essential
what matters what
what is alive and what is what is you
know what is hubios and what is
what is false um what is good faith and
what is
bad faith precisely precisely because it
because it creates
because it creates the bridge of
continuity between the frame
and as it's a transframing device right
it
is it is the continuity between what is
enclosed within the frame
in in in this case the narrative within
this metaphor
and what is beyond the frame of the
narrative uh so
and and you're precisely right that the
the
the the the most the most apt
description
of that continuity is precisely the
relation of faith
yeah that's exactly right that's good
and then you get oh and then i think
what that does uh to invoke
uh both of your uh your sort of
uh familiar with catholicism
that's what tradition was supposed to be
tradition was your faithfulness to the
chorus that precedes
it is beyond you and pronounces upon you
continuously
um yeah like the host or something of
precisely well i mean in the liturgy
you always invoke the host the host of
all the people
not only all the people that that are
present visibly you invoke
all the invisible people that are
present all the salients all
i can say all those saints are made all
the angels and saints
all the angels and kings yeah the
heavenly
absolutely and also you so you come back
to being in a cosmos
uh again uh um not nothing you get
a wandering fragmented you know um
yeah person and then you you you find
yourself situated
in a mandala or a cosmos or in a world
again
to use heidegger's yeah i think so i
think so
yes i mean i i've always been struck but
spinoza has this notion of you know
we can find what he calls the face of
the universe
uh which is this sort of gestalting
thing
that allows us to enter into right
relationship with it
right and and so yeah i think it's doing
exactly that
we're back to the interfacing notion
again right
tradition is a powerful way in which we
interface
um with with the universe
and and make it as you said make it
cosmic for us
as opposed to just a a
an empty set of stuff thrown together
not an empty stat i'm going to say a
purely logic i might give me an empty
set i mean a purely logical or
terminally
purely formal set as opposed to a logos
the difference between a death star
sorry yeah yeah the difference between a
a you know a set is you you put any
any things into it they're just bound
together by the formal grouping
but the logo says they things are
grouped together so that they come to
belong together
and then and thereby and thereby they're
belonging to each other
is how they can include you and you can
participate their belonging to each
other is precisely how
you can belong to them
i should get going guys
[Laughter]
back to back to the the uh the world as
it is
the world as it is exactly
do you have anything else to say
christopher before
luindus no nope i'll let that be the
final word
okay well thank you so much uh that was
amazing um
thank you andrew thank you again for
convening us
and uh yeah it's it's great
so we talked about the soul this time
that was a
that was the word i threw in in the
beginning and and maybe if we do it
again sometime
i wonder what what's next i i like this
andrew actually i like this idea of
taking a pregnant topic
and then throwing it in and we do that
thing i talked about we
open it up and then we recollect it and
open up and recollect it
as opposed to just right forming the
circle
uh but actually centering the circle
upon
a chosen topic on it
i think the excellent thing we did what
i really like actually is this
this uh three three people um i find
it's
it's much more interesting for me uh in
these kind of conversations
if there's three people here it's seems
to be a such a
much more dynamic energy than just one
person against another person um
or so so that's one thing i really love
is this
trio i'm doing that with other people as
well
well you have the intimate chorus then
because yeah because yeah the chorus is
present when when
we're three for some reason yep exactly
we're we're more like we're on a stage
there's more than just two people that
yeah again and we're actually on a real
stage when there's three the chorus is
here
because that because because the symbol
of the third factor can emerge
more apparently right the third factor
yeah
it's a way of uh you know creating a
locus for the third factor
third factor to emerge very much right
and if there's a fourth person somehow
one person is kind of left out a little
bit
of the conversation or not always but
and if it's five it's just too many
so three seems beautiful what anyway
i'll let you go thank you so much guys
that was just uh
mind-blowing as as always and even more
so this time
well thank you andrew and again thank
you chris always wonderful to be in your
presence
thanks guys likewise